Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records 1815-2018 NYHS-RG 21
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society Library Department records
1815-2018
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 21
194.71 Linear feet in 340 boxes of various sizes and 54 shelved volumes
The New-York Historical Society Library Department records group includes a broad range of material related to the administration of the Library and its component sections, including the Reading Room, Manuscripts Department, Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, often referred to as the Print Room), and the Conservation Lab. The subject matter spans the entire breadth of the Library's activities: acquisition of materials for the collection, curatorial and conservation surveys and assessments, collection inventorying and cataloging projects, in-house exhibitions and outgoing loans, and patron access and use of the collections.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers, though some material is restricted. N-YHS restricts Board of Trustee and Executive Office files for 50 years following the departure of a President and Chief Executive Officer. This restriction pertains to portions of this record group. Also, the records related to patron research inquiries are restricted for a time. Any restrictions are further described in an Access Restrictions Note at the relevant series level.
The bulk of the material is stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Accruals Note
Accruals to the record group were added subsequent to the major 2016 processing of the record group and additional accruals are expected over time.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHSRG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society Library Department records (NYHS-RG 21) are as follows:
The N-YHS governance level minute books and so-called official papers include much material concerning N-YHS's library matters, especially with regard to acquisitions. For years through 1938, see: New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1). For years subsequent to 1938, see New-York Historical Society Board of Trustees records (NYHS-RG 18).
Library accessions were documented in ledgers from 1841-1962, with gaps. See New-York Historical Society collection accession registers (NYHS-RG 15).
N-YHS's central correspondence files include documents relating to all aspects of NYHS operations, including the library, from the institution's earliest days to 1982. The correspondence includes acquisitions, early reference inquiries, and other matters. See New-York Historical Society general correspondence (NYHS-RG 2). Some acquisition correspondence, especially related to bequests, but also gifts and some purchases, was placed with legal records; see New-York Historical Society legal matters (NYHS-RG 16).
The longtime assistant to Librarian Alexander Wall, Dorothy Barck was Librarian from 1942-1954. Her records are found in New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records (NYHS-RG 19).
There are many connections between N-YHS's library and museum, including collaborations on exhibitions, the transfer of the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture to the museum (1989) and back (1998), coordination of outgoing loans, and other matters. See New-York Historical Society Museum Department records (NYHS-RG 20).
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society Library records are organized in the following series:
Series I. Collection Descriptions & Inventories (1815?-2003)
Series II. Acquisition Records (1962-2001)
Series III. General Office Files (1959-2009, bulk 1980s-2002)
Series IV. Librarian & Curatorial Files (1959-2013)
Series V. Exhibitions (1969-2011, bulk 1992-2001)
Series VI. Outgoing Loans (1960-1992, bulk 1979-1992)
Series VII. Board Library Committee Matters (RESTRICTED IN PART) (1950-2015)
Series VIII. Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, a/k/a Print Room) (1940-2015, bulk 1970s-2013)
Series IX. Conservation (1989-2004)
Series X. Public Service (RESTRICTED IN PART) (1829-2011)
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society Library Department records group includes a broad range of material related to the administration of the Library and its component sections, including the Reading Room, Manuscripts Department, Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, often referred to as the Print Room), and the Conservation Lab. The subject matter spans the entire breadth of the Library's activities: acquisition of materials for the collection, curatorial and conservation surveys and assessments, collection inventorying and cataloging projects, in-house exhibitions and outgoing loans, and patron access and use of the collections.
The record group includes correspondence and memos, surveys, management reports, statistical information, policies, planning documents, budgets, appraisals, acquisitions (purchase, donation) and sales, contracts, visitor registers, grant applications and project implementation files, exhibition files (e.g., checklists, loan agreements, label texts), cataloging worksheets, and conservation reports. Most of these records date from the last three decades of the twentieth century and into the early twenty-first century (see the Related Materials Note for most earlier documents). An exception to this are the visitor registers; though there are sizable gaps in the nineteenth century, these records date from as early as 1838. The record group also holds nineteenth century admission tickets and calling cards used to introduce and permit non-members to use library resources.
The record group holds an array of collection descriptions and inventories compiled for various purposes over time, and these range from throughout N-YHS's history. For example, there is a circa 1826 inventory of maps, John Delafield's 1833 manuscript-form catalogue of the books in the library, the 1941 inventories of material sent off-site for storage during World War II, and a card catalog of comic books deaccessioned in the 1970s. Most of these inventories were prepared by N-YHS staff, but some in the record group were prepared by the collection donor or other outside party, such as the inventory of the Lathrop Colgate Harper Spanish-American War Collection distributed by Harper's estate.
New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Acquisitions (Libraries) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Librarians -- Correspondence.; Library exhibits -- New York (State) -- New York.; Library materials -- Collection and preservation -- United States.; Museum exhibits -- New York (State) -- New York.; Inventories.; Letters (correspondence); New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society. Library -- Management.
- Series I. Collection Descriptions & Inventories, 1815?-2003; 27.29 Linear feet in 46 boxes of various sizes and 3 shelved volumes
  Arrangement Note
  The Collection Descriptions & Inventories series is organized in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Descriptions Prepared by N-YHS
  Subseries I.B. Descriptions Prepared Outside N-YHS
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Collection Descriptions & Inventories series includes primarily manuscript form inventories, catalogues and other material describing the content of N-YHS's library collections. The bulk of these were prepared by N-YHS library staff from the nineteenth to early twenty-first century. Some inventories in the series were prepared by the original creator, donor, auction house, or other person outside of N-YHS. The series includes both standalone documents, such as John Delafield's 1833 catalogue of books in the library, and working files for projects requiring the inventorying or cataloging of the collections. The container lists include reference to the specific descriptive material in the files.
  Related Archival Materials Note
  The series includes only those standalone descriptions found with the library records in the N-YHS archives during processing. Inventories can be found in other record groups of the archive as well, perhaps especially the New-York Historical Society legal matters (NYHS-RG 16). Also some manuscript collections include the inventory supplied by the creator or donor.
  - Subseries I.A. Descriptions Prepared by N-YHS, 1815?-2003; 25.83 Linear feet
    The subseries includes primarily manuscript form inventories, catalogues and other material describing the content of N-YHS's library collections. The subseries includes many standalone documents from the nineteenth century, such as John Delafield's 1833 catalogue of books in the library and lists of manuscripts and maps from the 1820s.
    Material from the twentieth century ranges beyond inventories to include broader descriptions of the library collections, working files of cataloging and other projects involving collection descriptions, bibliographies and guides to the collection. These files include, among others, records of the collections sent outside of New York City for safekeeping during World War II, the index to a comic book collection deaccessioned in the 1970s, annotated typescripts of Arthur J. Breton's Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS, and the survey/inventory sheets from the NEH-funded project to catalog N-YHS's maps (1989-1994 ). In addition to the map project, several other cataloging or other collection classification and control projects from the 1980s-1990s are documented in the subseries. The container list includes reference to the specific descriptive documents in the files.
    The subseries is arranged in rough chronological order. Much of the nineteenth and early twentieth century material is undated; an approximate date is supplied based on the latest date of the items in the inventory or other indicators. Some map-related documents from the mid-1800s and later appear to have been used as source material for a 1990s NEH-funded cataloging project and were filed as found with that material.
    The NEH-funded map cataloging project of August 1992-December 1994 is shown in the container list in two segments, designated I and II. Segment I includes records from the pilot project and the records through early 1993 when the project was shut down when N-YHS closed its doors at the time. Segment II includes the reactivated project records from 1994, as well as some earlier records that were carried forward.
    Access Restrictions
    Some of the material related to the NEH-funded map cataloging project, specifically most of the survey and inventory worksheets, is expected to be stored offsite and requires advance notice to access.
    - Political Pamphlets of N-YHS, circa 1815? (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Duplicates in N-YHS Library, circa 1820? (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - List of Manuscripts in the Library of N-YHS, 1824 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Catalogue of Manuscripts Belonging to N-YHS, circa 1820s? (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Catalogue of Maps Belonging to N-YHS, circa 1826 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Includes a list of maps as well as records of loans of maps and their return to the Library. Includes a tipped-in letter from Joseph Delafield requesting a loan of particular maps in support of the United States's claims on the Northwest Territory under the Treaty of Ghent. See also folder below: Map Cataloging Project I (NEH). Maps & Charts for a nineteenth century inventory apparently referenced during the 1990s project.
    - Catalogue of the Books in the Library of N-YHS, 1833 May (Box 1, Volume 1)
      Compiled and arranged by John Delafield and presented to the Society.
    - Manuscripts of N-YHS?; Miscellaneous Revolutionary Papers, circa 1830s? (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Manuscripts in the N-YHS Library, circa 1840? (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Untitled [Accessions?], 1844? (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Catalogue of a Library [N-YHS?]. B-Z (2 folders), circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - Catalogue of a Library [N-YHS?]. F-Z, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Library Inventory?, 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 11a)
      Scope and Contents
      Handwritten list, alphabetical by title of volumes. (Added to record group in December 2020.)
    - Newspapers, circa 1849 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - [Collection Inventories] (1 of 21 folders). Associate Reformed Synod, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 13)
      The following set of folders contain inventories for various collections that were found boxed together by the processing archivist and appear to have been created by the same person. The circa date of 1840s is taken from the printed material that wraps some of the packets.
    - [Collection Inventories] (2 of 21 folders). Bayard; Bellomont, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - [Collection Inventories] (3 of 21 folders). Boundaries, New York and Massachusetts and New Jersey, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 15)
      See also the Collection Inventories-Various folder below for other boundary-related inventories.
    - [Collection Inventories] (4 of 21 folders). Colden, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - [Collection Inventories] (5 of 21 folders). Duer, circa 1840s? (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - [Collection Inventories] (6-11 of 21 folders). Gates (6 folders), circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 1-6)
    - [Collection Inventories] (12 of 21 folders). Horsmanden, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - [Collection Inventories] (13 of 21 folders). Indian Deeds, Transports & Conveyances (copies) in the Secretary's Office at Albany, Translated from the Original Dutch, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - [Collection Inventories] (14 of 21 folders). Sir William Johnson; Leisler; McKesson, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - [Collection Inventories] (15 of 21 folders). Allen McLane, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - [Collection Inventories] (16 of 21 folders). Miller; Osgood; Miscellaneous Revolutionary, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - [Collection Inventories] (17 of 21 folders). Lord Stirling, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - [Collection Inventories] (18 of 21 folders). Steuben, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - [Collection Inventories] (19 of 21 folders). Stewart; Williamson, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - [Collection Inventories] (20 of 21 folders). U.S. Military Philosophical Society, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - [Collection Inventories] (21 of 21 folders). Various, circa 1840s? (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Includes various lists, some headed but most not, found together with breaks between lists that are difficult to perceive. Headings include Schenectady papers, Revolutionary Army Orders, Boundary between New York & Connecticut, Salt Manufacture in North America, Mr. Trumbull's Maritime Opinions, Presbyterian Church in Wall Street, Military Journals of the French War, Plans for the Defense of New York City, and Lands Offered Society for Ameliorating the Condition of the Jews.
    - Catalogue of Almanacs, circa 1840s?-1960s (Box 340)
      Handwritten volume of almanacs, with entries entered as late as the mid-1960s.
    - Manuscript Catalogue. N-YHS. A-C, circa 1850 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Manuscript Catalogue. N-YHS. D-J, circa 1850 (Box 3, Volume 1)
    - Manuscript Catalogue. N-YHS. K-Q, circa 1850 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Manuscript Catalogue. N-YHS. R-Z, circa 1850 (Box 5, Volume 1)
    - Royal Society London Catalogue, 1850s? (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Untitled [List of Donations], circa 1854 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      Includes what appears to be a summary of accessions from 1809-1853.
    - Books Purchased for the Library by G.H.M. [George H. Moore], circa 1856-1859 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Loose sheets in booklet refer to some maps also and possibly to binding costs.
    - Draft Catalogue of Engravings, Photographs, Lithographs, Paintings, Statuary, & Medallions, circa 1860? (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Catalogue of the Gelston Collection, circa 1860? (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - De Peyster Collection. Catalogue of Books in the Library of N-YHS. Part I (Printed Pamphlet), 1868 January (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Catalogue of Magazines in the Store Room, circa 1870s-1880s (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Catalogue of the De Peyster Collection (4 folders), circa 1880? (Box 11, Folder 6-9)
      This version of the catalogue includes handwritten entries glued to pages. The 216 pages are brittle.
    - Catalogue of the De Peyster Collection, circa 1880? (Box 6, Volume 1)
      This version of the catalogue includes mostly entries cut from printed material and glued to the pages. There are handwritten additions.
    - Connecticut Election Sermons, circa 1880s? (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - U.S. Congressional Documents, 1880s? (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Society for the Propagation of the Gospel List of Sermons, 1880s? (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - U.S. Government Documents, circa 1885 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - List of Capt. Richard H. Green's Books in Basement, 1897-1913 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Folder includes lists of books and genealogical information.
    - Magazine Subscriptions, 1902-1916 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - New York State Documents, circa 1910? (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Regimental Histories of the War of the Rebellion, etc., circa 1910? (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Ordination, Funeral and Thanksgiving Sermons, Not Catalogued, circa 1910? (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Indicates that the sermons were mainly those purchased from Thomas J. Taylor of Taunton, Mass.
    - Untitled. [Miscellaneous Documents] (8 folders), 1800s-circa 1920s? (Box 18, Folder 1-8)
      These folders include various lists, descriptions, notes, clippings, a few letters, cards, labels, and other documents. These were found together by the archivist and kept as found. The documents as a whole appear to be a mix of materials used perhaps to summarize some accessions, identify gaps in holdings, form shelf location guides, develop catalog records, and other purposes. There seems no overall coherence to the whole or to the overall content of each folder, but some individual documents might be useful in their accession or other references.
    - King Collection, 1921 May (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Survey of the Manuscript Collections in N-YHS (Printed document, with annotations), 1941 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Wartime (WWII) Storage Shipments (5 folders), 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-5)
      Includes the original inventory of the library and museum materials shipped off-site for storage during WWII, a copy of the inventory with annotations relating to the return of the materials to N-YHS, lay-out of the storage locations, and working papers.
    - Almanac Survey, circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - List of Books Presented by the Beekman Family Association, 1948 November 24 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Kilroe Papers, Items Added in 1950 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - DeWitt M. Lockman Fiction Collection, circa 1950? (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Items Sent to Parke-Bernet Galleries, 1952-1953 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (7 of 17 folders), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1-7)
      This set of 17 folders includes the manuscript of Breton's Guide, both text and index, marked-up for publication and returned to N-YHS by Greenwood Press.
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (7 of 17 folders), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-7)
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (3 of 17 folders), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - Arthur J. Breton. Notes, circa 1972 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 4)
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (Vol. 1 in 2 folders), circa 1972 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 5-6)
      This disbound volume and the following three bound volumes include photocopies of Breton's entries with red underlining, possibly indicating potential headings for the index.
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (Vol. 2), circa 1972 (Volume RG21.1, Folder -)
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (Vol. 3), circa 1972 (Volume RG21.2, Folder -)
    - Arthur J. Breton. "Guide to the Manuscript Collections of N-YHS" (Vol. 4), circa 1972 (Volume RG21.3, Folder -)
    - Index to Deaccessioned Comic Books (1 of 2 boxes), 1970s (Offsite-box 7, Cards 1-3)
      This first box holds the A-Z index of comic books owned, by volume and number. The entry for each book includes a list of the features for that issue. This box and the next also hold an A-Z index by feature title, linking it to the relevant book title/issue. The entries are on oversize slips of paper held by metal prongs. Because of the way the slips are secured some may be difficult to read fully; should those cards need to be read, the preservation lab should be consulted for document access. It is possible that these cards were compiled, not by N-YHS, but by the creator/donor of the collection.
    - Index to Deaccessioned Comic Books (2 of 2 boxes), 1970s (Offsite-box 8, Cards 1-3)
    - Magazines & Newspapers Received by N-YHS, 1979 August (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Cataloging Project (NEH) (5 folders), 1982-1986 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-5)
    - Print Room Collection Guide. Public Version, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Print Room Collection Guide. Curator's Copy (2 folders), 1983 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - RLG Conspectus Worksheets. Art & Architecture, 1983-1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 3)
    - Inventory of Uncataloged Material (RLG Survey), 1986 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 4)
    - Current Periodicals in the Library, circa 1987 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 5)
    - Collections. General & Specific Descriptions, 1986-1989 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 6)
      Includes a (disbound) binder of various documents with fact sheets, general holdings descriptions and some of specific collections, collecting policies, and stack location lists.
    - Review of the Catalogued & Uncatalogued Collections in the N-YHS Stacks, 1989 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 7)
    - Collections Notebook (2 of 4 folders), 1980s (Offsite-box 13, Folder 8-9)
      Includes (disbound) binder of material including a procedural handbook and descriptions and inventories of particular collections. Appears to have been compiled over time in the1980s but includes photocopies of earlier material. Some of the originals of these copies are also in this series in the above folders.
    - Collections Notebook (2 of 4 folders), 1980s (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Diagrams of Stacks & Collection Locations (Oversize), 1990? (Box OS-1, Folder 20)
    - New York City Atlas Inventory, 1990 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 3)
    - N-YHS Archives. Archiva Report, 1991-1992, 1999 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 4)
      Includes the contents of a binder plus related reports. Includes archivist Tom Dunnings's survey of the institutional archive as of 1991, a call number system (1992), and the report and inventories prepared by archival consultants Archiva in 1999.
    - Retrospective Catalogue Conversion (RECON) (4 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 5-8)
    - Map of Stacks, 1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 9)
    - Policies & Procedures of the Library, circa 1991 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1)
      Includes overview descriptions of the library, its collections, public service statistics, and preservation strategies.
    - Bibliography. African-American History. Items in N-YHS Collections Suitable for Exhibit, 1992 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 2)